<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: creativity | ]]></title>
  <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/blog/categories/creativity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-23T09:11:48-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://fooqri.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Patrick Goddi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pattern problems vs logic problems]]></title>
    <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/18/pattern-problems-vs-logic-problems/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-18T11:48:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/18/pattern-problems-vs-logic-problems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Suppose three men can paint three fences in three hours. How long would it take one man to paint one fence?</p></blockquote>

<p>I ran across this interesting problem in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Joy-Guided-Infinity-ebook/dp/B006R8PL7G/ref=tmm_kin_title_0">&ldquo;The Joy of x: A Guided Tour of Math, from One to Infinity,&rdquo;</a> a very accessible and interesting tour of mathematics.</p>

<p>It turns out most people quickly answer “one hour.”  As Strogatz opines,</p>

<blockquote><p>The words themselves nudge you that way. The drumbeat in the first sentence— three men, three fences, three hours— catches your attention by establishing a rhythm, so when the next sentence repeats the pattern with one man, one fence, ____ hours, it’s hard to resist filling in the blank with “one.” The parallel construction suggests an answer that’s linguistically right but mathematically wrong.</p></blockquote>

<p>The correct answer is three hours. It is obvious if you imagine each person painting their own fence for three hours. Remove two people and two fences and you are left with one person, still painting their one fence for three hours, as before.</p>

<p>What struck me about this problem is that it is an incredibly simple, concrete, and visual example of how our brains try to match patterns, but more importantly the side effect that occurs when a pattern is matched. Neuroscience studies suggest that dopamine (a neurotransmitter associated with pleasure) is released when we solve a problem, thus giving us a biological explanation for that wonderful feeling we get when we have solved a problem.</p>

<p>This made me wonder, does our brain perhaps release dopamine when we solve the faux pattern matching problem and <em>tricks</em> us into thinking we solved the actual logic problem? Thus we quickly blurt out the wrong answer.  After all, we have spent a lifetime feeling the dopamine rush when we believe we have the answer to a problem. Strogatz&rsquo;s observation about this particular word problem having two solutions (a pattern solution, and a logic solution) is very interesting, and is likely very related to a number of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_biases_in_judgment_and_decision_making">Cognitive Biases</a>. It is perhaps valuable to think about this explicitly when considering information:</p>

<ul>
<li>What is the pattern problem being suggested?</li>
<li>What is the logic problem being suggested?</li>
</ul>


<p>And make sure you have the answer the right question when you feel that first burst of dopamine show up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creativity Booster: Get a dog.]]></title>
    <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/17/creativity-booster-get-a-dog/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-17T12:47:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/17/creativity-booster-get-a-dog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It probably sounds specious, but I have found having a dog around has made me both more productive and more creative. The evidence for this claim is the number of daily messages I post to our team message board that start with the phrase &ldquo;While I was out walking the dog I had this idea&hellip;.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Before getting a dog I would get sucked into a problem and become obsessed with solving it, the kind of linear obsession that leaves no room for creative leaps. What is needed is to allow the problem to marinate in my subconscious, to facilitate the unexpected synaptic connections that occur when you finally let your mind relax. The problem is, obsession with solving the problem makes this type of relaxed mind difficult and leaps of creativity less frequent. I am sure with practice one could recognize the symptoms and use some type of mediation exercise, but for me the answer is walking the dog. The pattern repeats regularly &hellip; I hit a nasty bug or design conundrum, get stuck, and then take the dog out for 15-20 minutes, and the answer suddenly presents itself.</p>

<p>For me, dog walking seems to engage the kind of subconscious pattern matching that provides the keys to unlock many problems. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graham_Wallas">Wallas</a> would have called this the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creativity#Incubation">incubation</a> phase of creativity. I think of it as a cousin to Mihály Csíkszentmihályi&rsquo;s concept of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology">flow</a>) mental state. This seems to be validated by Nardi&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MGfhQTbcqmA">work</a> on the neuroscience of personality. Specifically, the brain imaging results where he describes the delta state in terms of Csíkszentmihályi&rsquo;s flow, but adds that &ldquo;also on occasion when we are copacetic, open to whatever comes next.&rdquo; This is a perfect description of my mental state on a walk with the dog. I feel close to that feeling of flow, but not quite the same &mdash; an approximation. But it seems to do the trick. As a side note, Nardi’s brain imaging results of people watching TV shows up as black; similar to a deep non-dreaming sleep. So TV is not so good for creativity &hellip; just saying.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t find that walking alone or with another person works as well. I wonder if it is the non-conversational interactions with the dog, just enough interaction to get me to stop focussing on the issue, but not so much that my mind is focussed on keeping up a conversation with someone else. Whatever the reason, it works; almost always presenting a promising new direction, if not an outright answer.</p>

<p>This is my muse, Archer, the retired racing greyhound.</p>

<p><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/cfdcc46c180984c7ab7e3d43cb14a116/tumblr_inline_mgs53cHq981qz562v.jpg" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
