<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tips | ]]></title>
  <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/blog/categories/tips/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-18T18:43:34-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://fooqri.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Patrick Goddi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alfred + Pinboard + Chrome]]></title>
    <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/13/alfred-plus-pinboard-plus-chrome/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-13T12:29:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/13/alfred-plus-pinboard-plus-chrome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you happen to use <a href="http://www.alfredapp.com/">Alfred</a>, <a href="http://pinboard.in">Pinboard</a>, and Chrome, here is a nice extension to save the current browser page to Pinboard using Alfred. Much faster than any chrome extension, and fingers never leave the keyboard.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.timbueno.com/2012/06/27/pinboard-plus-alfred">Tim Bueno&rsquo;s Pinboard Extension</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Toggle Bluetooth]]></title>
    <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/08/toggle-bluetooth/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-08T12:10:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/08/toggle-bluetooth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my home office I have a Bluetooth keyboard and trackpad. When I use my MacBook Air elsewhere in the house I constantly see connect and disconnect messages for these devices. Frequently toggling BT on/off can be a pain; the menu bar method for toggling BT requires scanning the menu bar for the BT glyph, clicking on it, finding the correct menu item and clicking on it. All that scanning, tracking, and clicking can be disruptive to a good mental flow; I wanted a quick keyboard shortcut to toggle bluetoooth on/off. I use <a href="http://www.alfredapp.com/">Alfred</a> and after a quick search I found <a href="http://seapy.com/1779">this</a> extension that does just that. I use “bt” as the shortcut code. I have found this to be very handy, I now toggle out of habit, so no thinking required;</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.alfredapp.com/">Alfred App</a></li>
<li><a href="http://seapy.com/1779">Alfred Toggle Bluetooth Extension</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Syntax Highlighting in OS X quick look]]></title>
    <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/08/syntax-highlighting-in-os-x-quick-look/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-08T11:15:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/08/syntax-highlighting-in-os-x-quick-look</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Quick Look is a handy OS X feature where you can get a quick look at a file by selecting it and pressing the space bar. This is handy when looking through snippet files on disk.  <a href="http://goo.gl/KLW5t">This plugin</a> adds syntax highlighting in Quick Look supporting many common programming languages, and even supports R code.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting a quick definition]]></title>
    <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/05/getting-a-quick-definition/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-05T11:10:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2013/01/05/getting-a-quick-definition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am a logophile, and regularly looking up the meanings of words I encounter on the web or in pdf documents. More recent OS X versions include a great feature that allows you to get a quick definition in almost any app (browser, editor, etc). Highlight a word and press <em>ctrl-command-d</em> to get the definition of the word. It is easy to configure to include Wikipedia definitions so you can also look up people and concepts.</p>

<p>To customize which dictionaries are used (including wikipedia entries) open spotlight (command-space), type dictionary and press return to open the dictionary app. Open the preferences menu and tick the checkbox for the sources you wish to use. Once you make pressing <em>ctrl-command-d</em> a habit you will find using it is very natural, and requires little thought to remember it.</p>

<p>Make sure you have wikipedia configured and then try it on these:</p>

<ul>
<li>crepuscule</li>
<li>quiescent</li>
<li>Malta</li>
<li>Thomas Bayes</li>
<li>Markov chain</li>
</ul>


<p>The pop-up definition is interactive so click on a definition to see the full definition entry then use the back arrow to get back to the list of definitions. You can also click on the source title to open the dictionary app with that entry.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
