<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: polymer | ]]></title>
  <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/blog/categories/polymer/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-11T06:15:21-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://fooqri.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Patrick Goddi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[d3 charts - wrapping 'NVD3 Charts' in a web component]]></title>
    <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2014/10/17/d3-charts-wrapping-nvd3-charts-web-component/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-17T06:39:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2014/10/17/d3-charts-wrapping-nvd3-charts-web-component</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my continued experiments with <a href="https://www.polymer-project.org/" target="_blank">Polymer</a>, I created a web component that wraps  <a href="http://nvd3.org/" target="_blank">NVD3</a> &ndash; a reusable chart library for  <a href="http://d3js.org/" target="_blank">d3.js</a>.
As part of the activity I ported all of the  <a href="http://nvd3.org/examples/index.html" target="_blank">NVD3 example charts</a> to a web component I am calling <em>&lt;goddip-charts></em>. The component is contained in a <a href="http://www.poggr.com/pekqyTpXDEe:deJoY70GdVx" target="_blank">pogg</a> on <a href="http://www.poggr.com/home/" target="_blank">poggr.com</a>, as this is where I do my experimenting and it allows me to code and serve the project documents in the one place.</p>

<iframe width="680px" height="380px" src="http://www.poggr.com/pg1GXbi9MBx:dlym9bhp4Lx::53"></iframe>


<p></p>

<p>The above chart is an iframe to <a href="http://www.poggr.com/pg1GXbi9MBx:dlym9bhp4Lx::53" target="_blank">this document</a> The actual element tag used is as follows:</p>

<pre><code> &lt;goddip-charts  
   class="small-chart-styles"
   chartType="bar"
   context="/pg1GXbi9MBx:deyDCclAEUg::53" 
   css="/pg1GXbi9MBx:dxkNM7ZicfBe::53" &gt;
 &lt;/goddip-charts &gt;
</code></pre>

<p>To view the uncompiled and unminified source see (<a href="http://source.poggr.com/pg1GXbi9MBx:dlym9bhp4Lx::49" target="_blank">html document source</a>, <a href="http://source.poggr.com/pg1GXbi9MBx:deyDCclAEUg::49" target="_blank">data document source</a>, and <a href="http://source.poggr.com/pg1GXbi9MBx:dxkNM7ZicfBe::49" target="_blank">style document source</a>).</p>

<p>The best way to learn about the <em>&lt;goddip-charts></em> component is to take a look at its <a href="http://www.poggr.com/pg1GXbi9MBx:dgJXG7boqzSe" target="_blank">README document</a>. This describes how to use each of the charts, reference data, add styling, etc. You can always view the component <a href="http://source.poggr.com/pg1GXbi9MBx:dlJkI7k9tBe" target="_blank">source</a>. If you have a <em>poggr.com</em> account you can view, clone, and edit <em>goddip-charts</em> using the <a href="http://project.poggr.com/pg1GXbi9MBx" target="_blank">poggr project UI</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spreadsheet Driven Web Apps]]></title>
    <link href="http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2014/10/15/spreadsheet-driven-web-apps/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T14:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://fooqri.github.io/blog/2014/10/15/spreadsheet-driven-web-apps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://fooqri.github.io//fooqri.poggr.com/pgyUYTfcMUe:dgyFhkQ9M8e"><img src="http://fooqri.github.io//s3.amazonaws.com/goddip-poggs/pgyUYTfcMUe/example_screen.png"></a></p>

<p>Using Google spreadsheets is a great way for a team to collaborate on a data set but it leaves a bit to be desired on presentation of the data. To that end I will be creating a series of fun examples showing how to build small interactive apps that utilize <em>Google Docs</em> and <em>Polymer</em> web components to quickly bring data to life. In this series I will be using a Google spreadsheet as the data source, but other data sources are possible, and I will get to those as well in future posts.</p>

<p>The first example is  <strong><em><a href="http://fooqri.poggr.com/pgyUYTfcMUe:dgyFhkQ9M8e">Hipster List</a></em></strong>, an app that shows cool places to visit in various cities. Check out the <strong><em><a href="//fooqri.poggr.com/pgyUYTfcMUe:dxJgUYaGcGUl">README</a></em></strong> document for details on how this app is put together.</p>

<p><a href="http://fooqri.github.io//docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0Ahy9ODkMXc1GdHRaTlI3Y2EydllTa2NsRjlxRVhMRlE&usp=sharing#gid=0"><img class="spreadsheet-screen" src="http://fooqri.github.io//s3.amazonaws.com/goddip-poggs/pgyUYTfcMUe/spreadsheet_screen.png"></a></p>

<p>A little convention is used to make it work. Namely, I use a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0Ahy9ODkMXc1GdHRaTlI3Y2EydllTa2NsRjlxRVhMRlE&amp;usp=sharing">Hipster Hot Spots</a> Google spreadsheet, where each city&rsquo;s data is represented by a tab in the spreadsheet. There is also a <em>key</em> tab that provides a list of all the cities in the spreadsheet and the tab id (<em>gid</em>) for each city&rsquo;s data. The app will load its data from the spreadsheet and populate the city drop-down list of <em>hot spots</em>, and display a map with markers for each <em>hot spot</em>. This was a fun first example, remember to checkout the <a href="//fooqri.poggr.com/pgyUYTfcMUe:dxJgUYaGcGUl">readme document</a> for code and explanation.</p>

<p><strong>Note</strong>: I enabled url fragment parameters so you can easily point the app at your own copy of the spreadsheet for testing. See the <a href="//fooqri.poggr.com/pgyUYTfcMUe:dxJgUYaGcGUl">readme document</a> for the how-to instructions. Feel free to copy the spreadsheet and try out the app with your own list of cities and <em>hot spots</em>.</p>

<p> Separating code and data is always beneficial, but there is something cool about connecting an app to a Google spreadsheet. There are many spreadsheet users who would like to have an app to visualize their data, but may not be up to the coding challenge yet. I think many small useful apps could be built this way;  I will pick a few to build in the next few weeks and discuss them here. I am using the <em><a href="//www.poggr.com/home">poggr.com</a></em> service for the example, which is a service I built just for these types of small quick apps that can rely on an external data service. It is basically working to merge interactive content creation and blogging into a single service.</p>

<p> Leave me a comment if you have an small spreadsheet driven app you would like me to build. If it seems reasonable I may add it to the list.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
